Ling Dong,
来了
I stumbled upon this awesome book
我发现一本好书啊
called "Border Town",
叫 边城
and it's a special edition.
还是纪念版
Want it? I'll buy you a copy.
你要不要 我送你一本
Just read it when you...
回去你就可以照着这个
I'll check it out later.
等会儿再看
30-Day Winter Break Homework?
寒假冲刺三十天
Seriously?
至于吗
Take it.
拿着
Keep it for yourself.
自己没手啊
You gotta do
基础练习
some basic drills.
还是要做一下的
This is crazy thick!
这这这都这么厚了
Basic drills, huh?
还叫基础练习
Looks like we have
我觉得你对厚
different definitions of "thick".
是不是有什么误解
So heavy!
这么沉
Okay.
可以
These should
这些应该
be enough for now.
暂时差不多够了
You straight A students
你们这些学霸
really grind hard
为了拿第一
just to
真是付出了
top the charts.
常人无法忍受的艰辛
What?
你想什么呢你
These are all for you.
这都是给你的
Why the look?
怎么
Slogans
你以为口号
won't cut it.
就是喊喊就得了
From tomorrow, I'm giving you
为了你的高考成绩
private lessons for college prep.
从明天开始我给你补课
It's just the beginning of winter break!
可是寒假才刚刚开始啊
But didn't you just say
可是你不也是刚刚说过
you wanna get into Jing University?
你要考京大吗
What's up? Wanna go abroad instead?
怎么 难道你更想出国
No.
我不想
So do it.
那不就得了
You've got this, nephew.
好好加油吧 大外甥
Come on, you're the best,
真的不能通融通融吗
can't we ease into it?
循序渐进地来
Just
先做
a third of it, okay?
三分之一 可不可以嘛
Y... You'll pay for the books.
可以先把单买了
Right.
对了
The "Border Town" is quite good.
这本 边城 挺好的
Buy me a copy.
帮我带一本
You like it?
喜欢吗
Xiaohua?
小画
Why are you here?
你们怎么来了
We...
我们
Lan Jinghui is here to say thanks.
兰靖灰是来跟你道谢的
For what?
道谢
Thanks for
谢谢你
helping him out big time.
帮了他一个大忙啊
You helped too,
你不是也帮忙了吗
it's not just my doing.
又不是我一个人的
Okay. Enough.
好了 就不要再争了
I'm here
你师父我呢
mainly to
今天主要是来
say thanks
跟你表达一下谢意
and give you a nice present.
顺便给你送上一份厚礼
Is that so?
还有这么好的事
What kind of gift is it?
什么礼物啊
Essential Practices?
必刷题
I don't want it.
我不要
Xiaohua.
徒弟
This is a pack of knowledge!
这可是满满的知识哦
As the New Year is approaching,
新年马上就要来了
I'm giving you
你师父我只能送上你
the best gift I can think of.
最宝贵的新年礼物了
No gifts this year,
今年过节不收礼
it's
我我我
too much!
这么贵的礼我收不起
Starting tomorrow,
从明天开始
let's dive into the ocean
和师父一起荡漾在
of knowledge together, okay?
知识的海洋里吧 好吧
♪Let's sway twin oars.♪
让我们荡起双桨
Get to the point.
说重点
From tomorrow,
明天开始
let's hit the books at my place.
来我家一起补习吧
At your place?
去你家补习
The three of us?
我们仨
Yep.
没错
The study duo
我们之前的学习小组
showed us that
已经充分地验证了
learning together
大家在一起学习
is way more effective.
效率会更高
Of course.
当然了
If you don't feel like it,
如果你不愿意的话
no pressure.
我们也不勉强
No pressure.
不勉强 不勉强
No pressure at all.
一点也不勉强
I'm in.
我愿意
So
那
it's a "yes"?
你同意了
Friends stick together,
朋友一生一起走
but studying makes you a dog.
谁先学习谁是狗
Let's both be dogs while studying.
一起学习一起狗
Woof Woof Woof!
汪汪汪
Childish.
幼稚
You told me to say it!
不是你让我说的吗
Let's put in
那我们就这样
the effort
一起加油
and get into a great college.
努力考个好大学
Here.
那么
One.
三
Two.
二
Three.
一
Fighting!
加油
Hey.
来啦
You're Ling Dong?
你不是凌冬吗
Hey, Grandma.
奶奶好
Are you here to see Jinghui?
找小灰啊
We're supposed to study together today.
我们约好了一起补习的
Hey, Grandma. I'm Xiaohua,
奶奶好 我是肖小画
also from Lan Jinghui's class.
也是兰靖灰的同学
Hello, Xiaohua. Come in.
小画啊 那赶紧进来吧
Jinghui hasn't got up yet.
小灰呀 他还没起床呢
Grandma, what's for breakfast?
奶奶 今天早餐吃什么
Why are you here?
你们怎么来了
Didn't you
不是你约我们
invite us here?
一起在这儿补习的吗
You remember it, right?
你该不会是忘了吧
[Where are you going?]
你去哪儿啊
[To change my clothes.]
换身衣服
Don't bother,
别换了
this outfit suits you well.
这身挺适合你的
[Shut up.]
闭嘴
Good job.
可以 不错 有进步
I actually got them all right?
我居然都做对了
What about me?
那我呢
Why so many crosses?
怎么那么多叉
Check those
你自己看看
easy ones,
你那些基础题
I've taught you twice,
我都跟你讲了两遍了吧
why can't you get them
为什么肖小画就能做对
like Xiaohua?
你就不能呢
You know what they say,
你没听过那句话吗
"No bad students,
没有教不好的学生
just bad teachers."
只有不会教的老师
So it must be your fault.
所以肯定是你没有教好
We're both taught by Ling Dong,
那同样是凌冬教的
why can I ace it but you can't?
那为什么我能做全对呢
Xiao Xiaohua.
肖小画
You're really picking up
你现在真是把凌冬
Ling Dong's
这个嚣张劲
arrogance now.
给我复刻了啊
Just wait and see.
你给我等着
For mid-break.
中场休息嘛
Did I cover
类似的题型
similar questions like this before?
我是不是之前跟你讲过
Yeah.
讲过
Okay, check this out.
好 那你看这道题
You gotta pick
题目是选出正确的
the right one.
那一项
Among A, B, C, and D, I chose C.
ABCD我选的C嘛
Tell me why C is the correct answer.
告诉我为什么是正确的
There's no reason.
没有为什么啊
[ABCD...]
ABCD是
Tell me
来 你告诉我
why you chose this one.
为什么是这个
I chose the shortest one.
三长一短选最短嘛
Sorry.
抱歉
Grab me a towel.
拿个毛巾啊
Come with me.
跟我来
[For what?]
你干吗
Your pants are wet.
裤子湿了是不是不舒服
Try it on.
穿上这个
Much better.
果断就好多了啊
I'm taking it off.
我不穿这个
Don't.
别动啊
You look great
我发现你穿这个衣服
in this,
还挺好看的
it really suits you.
太适合你了吧
But
但是
it feels like something's missing,
总感觉差了一点什么
just a little bit.
就差那么一点
Perfect!
满分
I'll grab you a new pair of pants
我去给你拿条新裤子
and wash these for you.
顺便把你裤子洗了
[Cross your heart,]
那你可要替我保守秘密
don't tell anyone.
谁也不能说
Pinky swear!
我们拉钩
What are you looking at?
看什么呢
Is this you as a kid?
这张照片是你小时候
Come on,
拜托
I was this cute and charming
我小时候就长
even when I was a kid.
这么可爱迷人了好吗
Yeah.
是
Just like now,
跟你现在差不多
Little Lan.
兰三岁
Little Lan? What are you? Big Ling?
兰三岁 你很成熟吗
Put these on.
赶紧换上
I'll meet you downstairs.
楼下等你
Let's play.
我们一起玩吧
He's all quiet.
他都不说话
Let's skip him,
我们不跟他玩
he's a weirdie.
他是小怪物
Hey, weirdie. I'll play with you!
小怪物 我来陪你玩
I'm a clownfish.
我是小丑鱼
Hey, weirdie. Why the long face?
小怪物 你怎么了
His Rubik's Cube is missing.
他的魔方不见了
Don't be sad, I'll help you find it.
别难过 我帮你找
Hey, weirdie. I found it!
小怪物 我找到了
Here.
给
Thank you, Clownfish.
谢谢你 小丑鱼
So you were the clownfish.
原来你就是小丑鱼
Check this out.
看这个
What?
什么呀
The news is
新闻上说
talking about
今年咱们湘北市
a huge fireworks show
在除夕夜
on New Year's Eve in our city.
会举行盛大的烟花秀
I've never
我从小到大
witnessed anything
都还没有看过
like that before.
这么盛大的烟花秀
Wanna check it out?
那你想不想看
[I'm in,]
陪你一起
and Ling Dong too.
还有凌冬
I'd love to!
当然想了
But is it okay to go out
不过除夕夜
on New Year's Eve?
能行吗
Sure thing!
怎么不能行
No biggie.
除夕夜怎么了
We'll just say
当然可以
we're hitting the books,
大不了就说一块补习
no problem.
不行吗
I'm fine with it.
我是没问题
So
那
[you have any problems?]
你有问题吗
If you really can't make it,
如果你实在不行的话
I'll go
我就去找阿姨
ask your mom.
我去求求她
Forget it,
得了吧
you'll just mess things up.
你那叫帮倒忙
[I'm just being proactive.]
我这叫身先士卒
Alright. I'll talk to my mom
行 我会跟我妈说的
about spending NYE at your place.
今年在你家过年
Nice.
好啊
So
那我们可就
it's a deal.
这么说定了啊
NYE.
除夕夜
Yeah.
嗯
Firework show.
烟花秀
Watch it together.
一起看
Yes.
好
Yeah!
耶
Finish your work.
先把卷子做了
Okay.
好
Back to it.
快写
Doudou.
豆豆呀
Sorry.
对不起了
I can't be with you
姐姐今年不能陪你
on NYE this time.
一起过除夕夜了
[You're grinning]
你看你笑得
[like a Cheshire cat,]
都合不拢嘴了
[no sign of regret at all.]
丝毫没有一点歉意
Thinking of NYE with Ling Dong,
一想到能和凌冬一起过
can't stop smiling.
我能不开心吗
Right?
是不是
[Xiaohua.]
姐妹
[It's almost time for the first snow.]
马上就要初雪了
[You've missed]
你之前错过了
[so many chances before,]
那么多次机会
[make sure you seize this one.]
这次一定要把握住
We're only going back for a few days,
一共就回去几天
why all the stuff?
拿那么多东西干吗
It's a rare trip,
好不容易回去一趟
so what if I pack a bit more?
拿点东西怎么了
Jinghui.
小灰呀
Have you packed your things yet?
你的东西收拾好了吗
Granny, I'm skipping the hometown trip
奶奶 今年我就先不跟
for New Year's this year.
你们一块回家过年了
What?
说什么呢
What's
你小子
[your sneaky plan this time, kid?]
又打什么歪主意呢
Granny. I invited
奶奶 今年呢
Ling Dong and Xiaohua
我约了凌冬
to study at our place on NYE.
他们来咱们家上补习课
We made a deal.
我都跟他说好了
It's tight on schedule,
后面的功课太紧张
gotta grab every moment.
争分夺秒
Every moment?
还还还争分夺秒
Why are you still playing games?
争分夺秒还打游戏呢
I'm just taking a break,
我这不是忙里偷闲吗
squeezing in
就趁他们来之前
some game time
这点工夫
before they arrive.
赶紧抓紧玩一会儿
That's enough.
行了行了啊
You talk a good game.
说的比唱的还好听
But I know your tricks.
我还不了解你啊
[One moment's inattention,]
一天不看着你
[and you're up to no good.]
就给我闯祸
Hurry up and pack your bags,
抓紧时间收拾行李
we're leaving for the hometown.
跟我们一块回老家
If you don't get it,
你要是听不懂呢
I'm not gonna argue.
我也不想跟你说
It's holiday season,
大过年的
I don't wanna fight.
我不想跟你吵架
I...
我 我
[Jinghui's getting into studying,]
小灰刚有学习的劲头
[we should back him up.]
我们鼓励才是
[Jinghui.]
小灰啊
Learn up from your uncle.
好好跟二表舅学习啊
[Call me if you need anything.]
有什么事跟奶奶打电话
Yeah, Granny.
好嘞 奶奶
One more bag.
我还有一个包
I forgot it.
我怎么找没找到
Go get it for me.
去帮我把那个包拿来
Where?
在哪儿
[It's]
在那个
[next to]
床 床那个靠
[the coffee table]
那个 那个
[by the bed.]
那个茶几那边
Don't butt heads with your dad.
别跟你爸犟啊
[Good boy.]
乖啊
[Doing test papers]
我说咱们大过年的
[on NYE,]
还做试卷
ain't that a bit harsh?
是不是有点太缺德了
Who swore
当初信誓旦旦地
to Grandma
跟奶奶说
[that he'd hit the books?]
会好好学习的人是谁啊
What's the plan for tonight?
那咱们今晚什么安排
Classic night:
很传统
hot pot and firework show.
吃火锅 看烟花
Wanna make some dumplings?
那要不要包饺子
[It's a must-have for Chinese New Year.]
过年是要吃饺子的
Sure, definitely.
可以啊 必须可以
You make, I eat.
你们负责包 我负责吃
[Perfect teamwork!]
分工明确
Nice try.
你想得美
What do you...
怎么叫我想得美
It's my mom. Gotta pick it up.
我妈 我去接个电话
Go.
赶紧去接吧
Be right back.
我去接
Come on, can't you
我说大过年的
take a day off during the holiday?
能不能给自己放一天啊
Your eyes gotta be sore from all that.
天天做题你眼睛不疼吗
What's the connection
过年和我做不做题
between NYE and doing homework?
有什么必然的关系吗
No...
是
No connection.
是没有什么必然的关系
But it's New Year's Eve.
但除夕佳节
You should enjoy it.
应该好好享受
Studying's quite enjoyable.
我觉得做题挺享受的
Fine.
行吧
What I'm talking about
我认为的享受
is spending time with you guys,
是跟你们一块过
not these test papers.
反正没有这种试卷
What?
不是
We had a deal.
我们已经说好了呀
But mom...
可是 妈
Mom.
妈
Why the long face?
你怎么了
My mom wants me to go home.
我妈让我回家
What? Why?
不是 回家干嘛
You talked with her about this, right?
你不是跟你妈说好了吗
Yeah.
是说好了
Who knew she'd change her mind
谁知道她临时变卦
and insist I go home for dinner?
让我必须回去吃年夜饭
My mom also messaged me
我妈也给我发消息了
to come home.
说让我回家
What...
不
Don't look at me like this.
你们不用看我
You should go home.
那你们就回去呗
But
那 那
what about you?
你 你怎么办
What
什么
"what about me"?
什么我怎么办
Don't worry about me.
你们不用担心我
Why are you
为什么要
worrying about me?
为什么要担心我呢
I've been through it all.
我什么风浪没见过
Right?
对不对
And I'm used to
而且我一个人过年
spending New Year's
我经常这样
alone.
习惯了
Besides,
再说
my grandma and dad
我奶奶跟我爸已经
have left me plenty to eat,
给我留了很多东西
food's not an issue.
我自己一个人吃都吃不够
And I've got games
而且我还有很多
to keep me busy.
娱乐项目在家里玩
Right?
对不对
[Don't worry]
不用操心
[about me.]
真的不用操心
Chill, I'm good.
别关心我了 真的
Seriously.
我是认真的
Could you just stop staring at me?
能别看了吗
Back to work, okay?
那咱们先做题 行不行
Finish it and go home.
早点做完题早点回家
Alright.
好了
[Dumplings coming up!]
马上饺子好了啊
[No sneaky bites.]
不许偷吃肉啊
[Eat light, Datu.]
少吃点 大图
[Mom, I'm hungry.]
妈 我饿了
[Alright, babe.]
好嘞 宝贝
[Just a sec.]
马上就好 马上就好啊
[Chop-chop.]
快点
[Grab a snack.]
先吃点别的
[Will be ready.]
等我一会儿
[Just a minute.]
马上就好了啊
[Dumplings coming up!]
饺子快好喽
[Hurry.]
快点啊
[Here come the dumplings!]
饺子来喽
Here comes the fish!
鱼来喽
Put it here.
来来来 还有个鱼呢
May there be a surplus every year.
年年有余啊
Thank you, my son.
看我儿子 辛苦你了啊
It's nothing.
没事
You're really blessed.
还是你有福气
Alright, let's dig in!
来来来 我们开始
Pour some drink for your Auntie.
来来来 给你马姨倒上
Go ahead.
马姨倒上
Okay.
好好好
Thanks.
谢谢 谢谢 谢谢
I'm so happy.
高兴得都糊涂了
It's so kind of you.
太客气了
Here.
来来来
Alright.
好嘞
Mom.
来 妈
And pour some for me.
来 给妈也倒上
Happy New Year!
新春快乐啊
Starving.
饿了
Bring on the good stuff!
来个硬的
Hello?
喂
[Jinghui?]
小灰呀
Hey, what's cooking?
干什么呢
Got anything good going on?
做什么好吃的
Granny.
奶奶
Hot pot's on,
我们吃的火锅
Ling Dong and Xiaohua
然后凌冬跟肖小画
are beasts.
实在太能吃了
Gotta hurry,
如果我吃得慢的话
meat's
就夹不到肉
almost ready
对 我先不跟您说了
or
肉要熟了
they'll take it all.
我要再再再不夹的话
Talk to you later!
我就真夹不着了
Alright.
好好好
Make sure you fill up.
你多吃一点啊
[Right.]
对
[Convey my greetings to them]
转达奶奶对他们的问候
[and wish them a Happy New Year.]
问他们新春快乐
I will. Granny, bye.
谢谢奶奶 拜拜
Happy New Year.
新春快乐 奶奶
Look what we
你看我们给你
brought for you!
带什么来啦
Hey,
怎么了
are you
是不是要哭了
tearing up?
是不是感动得要哭了
Don't let those tears spill.
别把眼泪流出来啊
I'm not,
我没有
don't you worry about that.
你管我
Happy New Year.
新春快乐
[Xiaohua.]
姐妹
[It's almost time for the first snow.]
马上就要初雪了
[You've missed]
你之前错过了
[so many chances before,]
那么多次机会
[make sure you seize this one.]
这次一定要把握住
Ling Dong.
凌冬
I wanna tell you something.
我想给你说一件事
Heard that
听说
the first snow is
初雪的时候
perfect for...
最适合
What is it?
你想跟我说什么
I wanna say...
我想跟你说
Happy New Year!
新春快乐
[There aren't many beautiful things]
世界上美好的东西
[in the world,]
不太多
[only tonight's fireworks]
今夜的烟花
[and the smile on your face.]
还有烟花下笑起来的你
[Although I don't]
虽然有些话
[have the courage to say it now,]
我现在没有勇气说出口
[I know]
但
[I'll never forget]
十七岁新春的这个夜晚
[this 17th New Year's Eve.]
我想我会永远记得
Wow,
太帅了
who's this handsome kid?
谁家小孩这么帅
I'm so jealous
太羡慕他
of myself!
羡慕自己
[Jinghui.]
小灰灰
[What are you doing?]
干嘛呢
So vain.
臭美呢
Isn't this your friend's?
这是不是你同学的书
Forgot it on the table.
掉到了餐桌上面了
Yeah, it's my classmate Xiaohua's.
是 肖小画 我同班同学
Make sure to
记得啊
give it back tomorrow.
明天给她带过去
I will. Granny.
好嘞 放心吧 奶奶
Have some fruit.
自己吃点水果
Yeah.
好
[On the first day of school,]
开学第一天
[Ling Dong talked to me,]
凌冬和我说话了
[though]
虽然
[it was a bit awkward.]
场面有些尴尬
I was there too.
那天我也在啊
Why didn't she draw me?
怎么就不画我呢
[It'd be nice if Ling Dong]
凌冬要是知道
[knew what baby's breath stands for.]
满天星的花语就好了
Baby's breath?
满天星的花语
Ling Dong.
凌冬
[I'll secretly]
我甘愿做配角
[love you from the shadows.]
瞒着所有人继续爱你
[All the stars in the sky]
我携满天星辰以赠你
[can't match how much I love you.]
仍觉满天星辰不及你
What's going on?
什么情况呀
Xiaohua's got a bit of an edge.
小画有点非主流啊
She's got a thing for Ling Dong?
她是不是喜欢凌冬啊
Come do your homework after class.
下课之后过来做题
What am I lacking?
差哪儿了